Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Public Schools records, 1833-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Ann Arbor Public Schools Historic Records, 1853-1970
  - Administration
    - Data from and pertaining to the Ann Arbor Public Schools
      - 1924-1943 (Volume 14)
      - 1925-1932 (Volume 15)
      - 1930-1937 (Volume 16)
    - Michigan Centennial Exhibit of Ann Arbor Public Schools, 1876 (Box 1)
      ("containing description of buildings, school system, courses of study, statistics, examination papers & pupils, etc.")
    - Primary Council, 1927-1943; 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - School Caucus Records, 1923-1925 (Box 1)
    - Secretary's Book of Leader's Club, 1913-1925 (Volume 17)
    - State Superintendent's Report, 1872 (Box 1)
      (Oramel Hosford, Superintendent of Public Instruction)
    - Superintendents
      - Otto W. Haisley, 1924-1929; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Lawrence F. Krueger, 1947-1957 (Box 1)
  - Elections
    - Record of Elections and Meetings, 1933-1967; 6 volumes (Box 2)
    - Record of Annual School Election, 1968; 1970; 2 volumes (Box 2)
- Historic School District Records, 1865-1977
  Historic School District Records, 1865-1977 series contains documents, mainly meeting minutes, for school districts and for some individual schools with no particular rationale of content. The term "district" seems to have different definitions for different historic periods.
  - School Districts
    - Ann Arbor Township
      - District No. 5, Minutes, 1946-1956 (Box 3)
      - District No. 7
        - District Record, 1902-1910; 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - Director's Book of Records and Accounts, 1910-1930; 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - Correspondence, 1919-1925 (Box 3)
        - Secretary's Book of Accounting Records, 1930-1935; 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - Teacher Contracts, 1889-1896 (Box 3)
        - Teacher Term Reports, 1881-1893; 1895; 1897; 1902; 1905; 1907-1910 (Box 3)
        - Minutes of Popkins School Board, 1950-1956 (Box 26)
      - District No. 8
        - Record Book, 1838-1864; 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - Director's Book of Records and Accounts, 1921-1932; 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - Secretary's Book, 1932-1942; 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - Minutes, 1943-1956 (Box 3)
        - Geddes School, Board Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3)
      - District No. 16 fractional, Ann Arbor and Scio Townships
        - Director's Book, 1865-1877 (Box 3)
        - Minutes, 1928-1940 (Box 3)
    - Lodi Township
      - District No. 8 fractional, Minutes, 1939-1948; 1951-1954 (Box 26)
    - Salem Township
      - District No. 6, Statistical Report, 1903 (Box 3)
    - Scio Township
      - District No. 4, Minutes, 1951; 1954 (Box 3)
      - District No. 5, Minutes, 1945-1957 (Box 3)
    - Superior Township
      - District No. 2, Minutes, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
    - Webster Township
      - District No. 1 fractional, Minutes, 1913-1930; 1934-1952 (Box 3)
  - Individual Schools
    - Bach School, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Braun School, Minutes, 1963-1965 (Box 3)
    - Dixboro School, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Eberwhite School, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Glacier Way-Green Road Elementary, Proposed Educational Specifications, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Haisley School, 1954; 1959 (Box 3)
    - Logan School, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Pioneer High School, Student Handbook, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Platt School, Minutes, 1943-1945; 1950 (Box 3)
    - Scarlett School (Box 3)
      (Mary Lyon Scarlett)
    - Tappan Junior High Camp, 1931 (Box 3)
    - Wines School (Box 3)
- Pittsfield Township, 1833-1960
  Pittsfield Township, 1833-1960 series contains the earliest records of this collection. Annual reports, teacher term reports, teacher contracts, financial reports, and meeting minutes together form a detailed picture of the functioning of the early Ann Arbor schools before separate districts merged.
  - Historic Records
    - Teacher Contracts
      - Contract Book, 1881-1900; 1 volumes (Box 3)
      - 1859, 1903-1904; 1906; 1908 (Box 3)
    - Teacher Term Reports
      - 1876 (Box 3)
      - 1882-1893 (Box 3)
      - 1898-1899 (Box 3)
      - 1905-1910 (Box 3)
      - 1928 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous documents
      - State publications, 1857; 1859; 1904 (Box 3)
      - Contracts, 1859 (Box 3)
      - Accountings, 1880 (Box 3)
      - Qualified Teachers, in Washtenaw County, 1889 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1895 (Box 3)
    - Minutes
      - 1837-1886, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1926-1935 (Box 4)
      - 1935-1941 (Box 4)
      - 1945-1958 (Box 4)
      - 1946-1949, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1949-1950, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1951-1953, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1953-1957, 1 volumes (Box 4)
  - Financial Records, 1872-1958
    - Assessor's Account Book, 1872-1913; 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - Director's Account Book, 1947-1952; 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - Annual Audits, 1946-1957 (Box 5)
    - Land Acquisition, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Appraisals
      - Pittsfield Village and Platt Road School, 1949 (Box 5)
      - Proposal for Appraisal Services, 1953 (Box 5)
      - Platt, Pittsfield, Mitchell Schools, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Annexation, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Sale of community school property by Pittsfield District, 1955 (Box 5)
    - East Ann Arbor Schools, 1949; 1953-1956 (Box 5)
    - Martha D. Mitchell Elementary School addition, 1957-1958 (Box 5)
  - Administration
    - Schools in Pittsfield Township, 1824-1974 (Box 5)
    - Survey of Pittsfield Schools, 1946
      - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 5)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 5)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 5)
    - Anniversary Celebration, 1951-1952 (Box 5)
- Administration, 1946-1991
  Administration, 1946-1982 series includes a wide range of organizational information on the post-war, modern school system in Ann Arbor. The series is divided into time periods that coincide with the records. The period 1968-1970 was well documented through the inclusion of the records of the superintendent, Scott Westerman, whose working files are made available here. The purchase and sale of properties and construction of new schools are documented as well as studies and reports on projects.
  - 1946-1959
    - Organizational
      - Departmental minutes and reports, 1947-1953
        - Audio Visual Aids Committee (Box 5)
        - Commercial Department (Box 5)
        - English (Box 5)
        - Home Economics (Box 5)
        - Industrial Arts (Box 5)
        - Instrumental Music (Box 5)
        - Music Department (Box 5)
        - Science Committee (Box 5)
        - Social Studies Department (Box 5)
      - Mathematics Department Minutes
        - 1944-1955 (Box 5)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 6)
        - 1961-1962 (Box 6)
        - 1965-1967, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Carpenter School Minutes, 1952; 1956-1958 (Box 6)
      - Dixboro Board of Education Minutes
        - 1952-May, 1956 (Volume 18)
        - 1956-February, 1958 (Volume 19)
        - School Building Program Clippings, 1953 (Box 6)
      - Special Election, 1953 (Box 6)
      - Salary Schedule, 1954 (Box 6)
      - Sale of High School, 1955 (Box 6)
      - School Policies
        - Policy Book, revised, 1949 (Box 6)
        - Policy Book, revised, 1952 (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous policies, 1943-1957 (Box 6)
        - Policy Book, revised, 1958 (Box 6)
      - Special Meetings, 1948-1957 (Box 6)
      - Stone School Minutes, 1953-1956 (Box 6)
    - Topical
      - Veterans Institute, 1946-1949 (Box 6)
      - Follow Up Study of 1947 Graduating Class, Ann Arbor High School, 1949 (Box 6)
      - Ann Arbor Educational Planning Conference, 1950 (Box 6)
      - Budget Information Day, 1959 (Box 6)
    - Committees
      - Elementary Steering Committee, 1948-1953 (Box 6)
      - Secondary Steering Committee, 1948 (Box 6)
      - Evaluation Committee, 1948-1953 (Box 6)
      - Fused Courses Committee, 1948-1951 (Box 6)
      - Geddes-Glacier Way Citizens Committee, 1954 (Box 6)
      - Junior High Coordinating Committee, 1950-1953 (Box 6)
      - Citizens School Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 6)
      - Rural-Urban Committee, 1950-1951 (Box 6)
  - 1960-1969
    - Organizational
      - Middle School Planning, 1963-1970 (Box 7)
      - Annual Report of the Principals, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
      - Ann Arbor High School Building Principal's Annual Reports, 1966/1967-1967-1968 (Box 7)
      - Annual Report, Office of Research, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Annual Report, Office of Research, 1968 (Box 7)
      - Budget and Data, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
    - Topical
      - Huron High School
        - Educational Specifications, October, 1963 (Box 7)
        - Progress Report, 1965 (Box 7)
          (Lane, Riebe, Weiland-Architects)
        - Economy Proposals, 1965 (Box 7)
        - Planning Notes, 1965 (Box 7)
      - Emergence of Elementary School Guidance Jean Henne, 1966 (Box 7)
    - Committees
      - Ad Hoc Committee of Ann Arbor High School Faculty, 1967 (Box 7)
        (Vinter-Sarri Research Report on School Dropouts)
      - Citizens Advisory Committee on School Finance, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Curriculum Review Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
      - Huron High School Biracial Committee, 1969 (Box 7)
      - Pupil Personnel Services Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - Scott Westerman, 1968-1970
    - Studies and Reports
      - Ann Arbor Split-Trimester Extended School Year Plan, June 1970 (Box 7)
        (feasibility study report, State of Michigan, Department of Education)
      - Departmental Annual Reports, 1968-1970; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Dropout Study, 1969 (Box 7)
      - EPDA, 1969-1970
        - In-Service Staff Development Project, 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Terminal Report to Department of Education, 1970 (Box 8)
          (DOE grant #465281)
      - IRMA, undated (Box 8)
        (Information, Resources, Materials, Assistance teacher handbook)
      - Waldenwoods Conference, December 13-14, 1969 (Box 8)
    - Superintendent's Records, 1969-1970
      (J-Z only)
      - J, K (Box 8)
      - L (Box 8)
        (including League of Women Voters)
      - M (Box 8)
        (including Michigan Civil Rights Commission, Michigan Department of Education, Middle School, Mitchell-Scarlett Woods)
      - N, O (Box 8)
      - P (Box 8)
        (including Parochiaid, Personnel, Public Library)
      - R (Box 8)
      - S (Box 8)
        (including Stone School Nursery, Student Demands, Students, Substitute Teachers)
      - T, U, V, W, Y, Z (Box 8)
    - Superintendent's Records, 1969-1970
      (outside agencies)
      - American Association of School Administrators (Box 9)
      - Ann Arbor, City and Township (Box 9)
      - Ann Arbor Organizations (Box 9)
      - Ann Arbor United Fund (Box 9)
      - Michigan Association of School Administrators (Box 9)
      - Michigan Association of School Boards (Box 9)
      - University of Michigan (Box 9)
      - Washtenaw Intermediate School District, 2 folders (Box 9)
        (includes Special Education Advisory Committee)
      - Washtenaw County Superintendents Association (Box 9)
    - Administrative Records, 1969-1970
      - Administrative Services, Richard Creal (Box 9)
      - Community Services, Dr. John Hubley, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Crossing Guards (Box 9)
      - Assistant Superintendent for Finance, Gerald Neff (Box 9)
      - Assistant Superintendent for Instruction, Dr. Sam Sniderman (Box 9)
      - Buildings and Grounds, Guy Finch (Box 9)
      - Business Manager, George Balas (Box 9)
      - Calendars, 1967-1969 (Box 9)
      - Director of Data Systems, Ivan Wagner (Box 9)
      - Director of Personnel, Stanley Zubel, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Human Relations, Ronald Edmonds (Box 9)
      - Master Agreement with Ann Arbor Education Association, 1968-1970 (Box 9)
      - Memos from Scott Westerman (Box 9)
      - Music, Lewis Wallace and Jack Morris (Box 10)
      - Occupational Education (Box 10)
      - Office of Instruction (Box 10)
      - Outdoor Education (Box 10)
      - Physical Education (Box 10)
      - Planner-Expediter, Sooren Gozmanian (Box 10)
      - Practical Nurse Training (Box 10)
      - Public Library, Homer Chance (Box 10)
      - Purchasing Agent, Richard Oberhausen (Box 10)
  - 1971-1976
    - Administrative Reports
      - Annual Reports of Directors and Subject Area Coordinators, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
      - Principals' Annual Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
      - Budget and Data, 1974-1975 (Box 10)
      - Buildings and Sites Needs Recommendations, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Educational Goals of Ann Arbor School System, December, 1974 (Box 10)
      - Human Relations, 1973-1976 (Box 10)
      - Humaneness in Education, 1971-1973 (Box 10)
      - Master Agreements with Ann Arbor Education Association, 1973-1974; 1974-1975; 1975-1978 (Box 10)
      - Relief of High School Overcrowding, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Committees
      - Committee to Eliminate Discrimination in Public Schools, 1972 (Box 10)
      - Principal Screening Committee Guidelines, 1971 (Box 10)
    - Projects, Studies
      - Ann Arbor Schools Study, 1974; 2 volumes (Box 10)
      - Feasibility of Ann Arbor Split-Trimester Plan, Terminal Report, July 1971 (Box 10)
      - Multi-Ethnic Curriculum Project
        (Title III-ESEA Project)
        - Manual, 1972-1975 (Box 11)
        - Manual, 1972-1976 (Box 11)
      - Teaching-Learning Communities, 1974-1976; 3 folders (Box 11)
        (Title III Project)
  - 1976-1991
    - Administration
      - Budget and Data, 1976-1977 (Box 11)
      - Demographic-Faculty Analysis Study, June 16, 1982 (Box 11)
      - Short-Range Planning Manual, 1976-1977 (Box 11)
      - Statistical Data-Staff and Students, 1976-1977; 1978-1979 (Box 11)
      - Superintendent Memos, Harry Howard, Richard Benjamin, 1983-1987 (Box 11)
    - North Central Association
      - Evaluation Reports, March, 1977 (Box 11)
      - Steering Committee Summaries, North Central Visitation, March, 1977 (Box 11)
    - Newsletters
      - The Grapevine, 1976-1991 (with gaps) (Box 11)
      - The Well News, 1986-1988 (Box 11)
      - Mini-Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 11)
      - PYSO Newsletter, 1985-1988 (with gaps) (Box 11)
- Desegregation, Jones School, 1965-1970
  Desegregation, 1965-1970 series documents the Jones School Study and efforts of the AAPS to create a more fair racial balance in the schools. Scrapbooks of clippings of that period are arranged chronologically and well-labeled.
  - Jones School Study
    - Reports
      - Jones School Study Rating Scales and Test Instruments, 1965 (Box 11)
      - Jones School Reassignment Project Master File, 1965-1966 (Box 11)
      - Jones Preschool Pilot Study, 1965-1966 (Box 11)
        (Gibson, O'Connor, Schwertfeger)
      - Annual Report, 1965 (Box 11)
      - Progress Report, 1967 (Box 11)
      - Final Report, 1969
        - Final Report (Box 11)
        - Documentation for Final Report (Box 11)
        - Code Manuals (Box 11)
        - Tabulations and Deck Lists (Box 11)
        - Requests for the study and other documentation, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
        - Birth Date Stats, 1965 (Box 11)
        - Census Attachment, 1966 (Box 11)
        - ITPA Class lists, 1966 (Box 11)
        - Scoring Keys (Box 11)
    - Presentations
      - Ann Arbor Board of Education presentations, 1966; 1968 (Box 12)
      - Original Overhead Transparencies copies (Box 12)
      - Dr. Carrigan, Office of Research presentation text (Box 12)
      - San Francisco State College colloquium, February 10, 1970 (Box 12)
    - Publicity
      - Distribution material (Box 12)
      - Correspondence (Box 12)
      - Memos (Box 12)
      - Press Releases and Articles (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Special Problems in Education, 1964-1967 (Box 12)
    - Civil Rights Issues, 1964-1967 (Box 12)
    - Civil Rights Issues, 1967-1969 (Box 12)
    - City, State, Nation, 1967 (Box 12)
    - City, State, Nation, 1967-1968 (Box 12)
    - City, State, Nation, 1969 (Box 12)
    - Clippings, 1972 (Box 12)
- Scrapbooks, 1933-1969
  Scrapbooks, 1933-1969 series contains a wide range of clippings about many aspects of the AAPS as portrayed in the local papers.
  - January 1933-September 1940 (Box 13)
  - September 1940-December 1944 (Box 13)
  - 1942 (Box 13)
  - January-May 1950 (Box 13)
  - May 1950-December 1951 (Box 26)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 14)
  - 1954 (Box 14)
  - 1955 (Box 14)
  - 1956 (Box 14)
  - 1957 (Box 15)
  - 1958-1960 (Box 15)
  - 1961 (Box 15)
  - 1962 (Box 15)
  - May-December 1963 (Box 16)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 16)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 16)
  - May 1964-May 1967 (Box 17)
  - July 1964-August 1967 (Box 17)
  - May 1967-August 1967 (Box 17)
  - August 1967-December 1967 (Box 17)
  - November 1967-October 1968 (Box 17)
  - December 1967-June 1968, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - June 1968-January 1969 (Box 18)
  - July 1968-May 1969 (Box 18)
  - July 1968-April 5, 1969 (Box 18)
  - January 1969-June 1969 (Box 18)
  - April 1969-December 1969 (Box 18)
- Miscellaneous other records
  The Miscellaneous other records series contains documentation of Ann Arbor High School alumni activities. Also of interest are minutes of meetings of the school's teachers, 1906-1922, and of the Board in Control of Non-Athletic Organizations, 1904-1938.
  - Board in Control of Non-Athletic Organizations, minute book, 1904-1938 (Box 19)
  - Ann Arbor High School alumni records
    - Alumni Association ledger containing membership fees, receipts and disbursements
      - 1919-1928 (Box 19)
      - 1929-1936 (Box 19)
    - Reunion minute book 1885-1891 volume also contains reunion register, 1860-1892 (Box 19)
    - Reunions register, 1902-1942 (Box 19)
  - Minute book of teachers' meetings, 1906-1922 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous: include by-laws of Ann Arbor High School Alumni Association; constitution of the Floriculture Club, and material relating to the Walter S. Perry Scholarship Fund (Box 19)